The conventional wisdom about our world today
الحكمة السائدة حول عالمنا اليوم
is that this is a time of terrible decline.
هي أن هذا الوقت يتّسم بالإنحطاط الفظيع.
And that's not surprising, given the bad news all around us,
وهو ليس بالشيء المفاجئ، بالنظر إلى الأخبار السيئة المحيطة بنا،
from ISIS to inequality,
بدءاً بتنظيم الدولة الإسلامية (داعش) حتى عدم المساواة.
political dysfunction, climate change,
والضعف السياسي، والتغيّر المناخي،
Brexit, and on and on.
وخروج بريطانيا، وغيرها الكثير.
But here's the thing, and this may sound a little weird.
ولكن الشيء الأهم، وقد يبدو هذا غريباً بعض الشيء.
I actually don't buy this gloomy narrative,
في الواقع، أنا لا أشتري هذه القصة الكئيبة،
and I don't think you should either.
وأعتقد أن عليكم فعل المثل أيضاً.
Look, it's not that I don't see the problems.
حسناً، ليس الأمر أنني لا أرى المشاكل.
I read the same headlines that you do.
أنا أقرأ نفس العناوين التي تقرأونها.
What I dispute is the conclusion that so many people draw from them,
نقطة خلافي هي الإستنتاج الذي يخرج به العديد من الناس،
namely that we're all screwed
أي أننا جميعاً محطّمون
because the problems are unsolvable
بسبب أن المشاكل غير قابلة للحل
and our governments are useless.
وأن حكوماتنا عديمة النفع.
Now, why do I say this?
الآن، ما الهدف مما أقول؟
It's not like I'm particularly optimistic by nature.
ليس الأمر أنني متفائل بطبيعتي.
But something about the media's constant doom-mongering
ولكن شيئاً يتعلق بالترويج الدائم للعذاب الذي تنتهجه وسائل الإعلام
with its fixation on problems and not on answers
مع تركيزها على المشاكل وليس الحلول
has always really bugged me.
لطالما كان يثير حفيظتي وبشدة.
So a few years ago I decided,
لذلك قررت منذ بضعة سنوات،
well, I'm a journalist,
حسناً، أنا صحفي،
I should see if I can do any better
لا بد أن أرى إن كان باستطاعتي إحراز تقدم
by going around the world and actually asking folks
بالسفر حول العالم وسؤال الناس
if and how they've tackled
عن كيف استطاعوا التصدي
their big economic and political challenges.
لتحدياتهم السياسية والإقتصادية الكبيرة.
And what I found astonished me.
وما وجدته أثار دهشتي.
It turns out that there are remarkable signs of progress out there,
اتضح أن هناك علامات تقدّم واضحة،
often in the most unexpected places,
غالباً في أكثر الأماكن غير المتوقعة،
and they've convinced me that our great global challenges
وقد أقنعوني بأن تحدياتنا العالمية العظيمة
may not be so unsolvable after all.
قد لا تكون غير قابلة للحل على الإطلاق.
Not only are there theoretical fixes;
ليست تلك الحلول نظريةً فقط؛
those fixes have been tried.
تلك الحلول تم اخضاعها للتجربة.
They've worked.
وقد نجحت.
And they offer hope for the rest of us.
وهي تعطي الأمل للبقية منّا.
I'm going to show you what I mean
سأريكم ما أعني
by telling you about how three of the countries I visited --
بالحديث عن كيف استطاعت ثلاث من الدول التي زرتها --
Canada, Indonesia and Mexico --
كندا وإندونيسيا والمكسيك --
overcame three supposedly impossible problems.
التغلب على ثلاث مشاكل من المفترض أنها مستحيلة.
Their stories matter because they contain tools the rest of us can use,
قصصهم مهمة لأنها تحوي أدوات يمكن للبقية منّا استخدامها،
and not just for those particular problems,
وليس فقط لحل تلك المشاكل المحددة،
but for many others, too.
ولكن للعديد غيرها أيضاً.
When most people think about my homeland, Canada, today,
اليوم، حينما يفكّر الكثير من الناس حول مسقط رأسي كندا،
if they think about Canada at all,
إن كانوا يفكرون فيها على الإطلاق،
they think cold, they think boring, they think polite.
فهم يفكرون أنها باردة ويفكرون أنها مملة ويفكرون أنها محترمة.
They think we say "sorry" too much in our funny accents.
يظنّنون أنا نردد كلمة "آسف" كثيراً في لهجاتنا المضحكة.
And that's all true.
وكل ذلك صحيح.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sorry.
آسف.
But Canada's also important
ولكن كندا مهمة أيضاً
because of its triumph over a problem
بسبب انتصارها على مشكلة
currently tearing many other countries apart:
تمزّق العديد من الدول حالياً:
immigration.
وهي الهجرة.
Consider, Canada today is among the world's most welcoming nations,
تعدّ كندا اليوم من ضمن أكثر دول العالم ترحيباً،
even compared to other immigration-friendly countries.
مقارنةً حتى بدول أخرى صديقة للهجرة.
Its per capita immigration rate is four times higher than France's,
معدل الهجرة للفرد الواحد أعلى أربع مرات منه في فرنسا،
and its percentage of foreign-born residents
والنسبة المئوية للمقيمين المولودين لأجانب
is double that of Sweden.
هي ضعف تلك في السويد.
Meanwhile, Canada admitted
في هذه الأثناء، استوعبت كندا
10 times more Syrian refugees in the last year
عشر مرات المزيد من اللاجئين السوريين في السنة الماضية
than did the United States.
أكثر من الولايات المتحدة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And now Canada is taking even more.
والآن تستقبل كندا المزيد حتى.
And yet, if you ask Canadians
ومع ذلك، إذا ما سألت الكنديّين
what makes them proudest of their country,
ما الذي يجعلهم الأكثر فخراً ببلادهم،
they rank "multiculturalism,"
سيصنّفون "التعددية الثقافية،"
a dirty word in most places,
كلمة قذرة في كثير من الأماكن،
second,
في المرتبة الثانية،
ahead of hockey.
قبل الهوكي.
Hockey.
لعبة الهوكي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In other words, at a time when other countries
بعبارة أخرى، في الوقت الذي تقوم فيه دول أخرى
are now frantically building new barriers to keep foreigners out,
ببناء حواجز جديدة على نحو جنوني لمنع الأجانب من دخولها،
Canadians want even more of them in.
يريد الكنديّيون استقبال المزيد منهم حتى.
Now, here's the really interesting part.
الآن، إليكم الجزء المثير للإهتمام حقاً.
Canada wasn't always like this.
لم تكن كندا هكذا دائماً.
Until the mid-1960s, Canada followed an explicitly racist immigration policy.
حتى منتصف الستينيات، اتبعت كندا سياسة هجرية عنصرية بوضوح.
They called it "White Canada,"
أطلقوا عليها اسم "كندا البيضاء،"
and as you can see, they were not just talking about the snow.
وكما ترون، لم يكن حديثهم مقتصراً على الثلج فقط.
So how did that Canada become today's Canada?
إذاً، كيف أصبحت كندا تلك هي كندا التي نعرفها اليوم؟
Well, despite what my mom in Ontario will tell you,
حسناً، رغم ما ستخبركم به أمي التي تقطن في أونتاريو،
the answer had nothing to do with virtue.
لم يكن للإجابة علاقة بالفضيلة.
Canadians are not inherently better than anyone else.
ليس الكنديّون على نحو موروث أفضل من أي أحد آخر.
The real explanation involves the man who became Canada's leader in 1968,
يشمل التفسير الحقيقي الرجل الذي أصبح زعيم كندا في العام 1968،
Pierre Trudeau, who is also the father of the current prime minister.
(بيير ترودو)، والد رئيس الوزراء الحالي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The thing to know about that first Trudeau
الشيء الذي يجدر بكم معرفته عن (ترودو) الأول
is that he was very different from Canada's previous leaders.
هو أنه كان مختلفاً تماماً عن زعماء كندا السابقين.
He was a French speaker in a country long-dominated by its English elite.
كان يتحدث الفرنسية في بلد تهيمن عليها النخبة الإنجليزية منذ أمد بعيد.
He was an intellectual.
كان مفكّراً.
He was even kind of groovy.
كما أنه كان رائعاً نوعاً ما.
I mean, seriously, the guy did yoga.
أقصد، على نحو جديّ، كان الفتى يمارس اليوغا.
He hung out with the Beatles.
وكان يقضي وقته مع فرقة (البيتلز).
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And like all hipsters, he could be infuriating at times.
ومثل كل محبي الموضة، قد يثير الحنق في بعض الأحيان.
But he nevertheless pulled off
ولكنه مع ذلك أنجز
one of the most progressive transformations any country has ever seen.
واحدة من أكثر التحولات تقدمية والتي لم تشهدها أي دولة من قبل.
His formula, I've learned, involved two parts.
الأسلوب الذي اتبعه، كما عرفت، اشتمل على قسمين:
First, Canada threw out its old race-based immigration rules,
الأول، تخلصت كندا من قوانين هجرتها القديمة القائمة على أساس العرق،
and it replaced them with new color-blind ones
واستبدلتها بأخرى لا تعير اللون اهتماماً
that emphasized education, experience and language skills instead.
والتي ركّزت بدلاً من ذلك على التعليم والخبرة ومهارات اللغة.
And what that did was greatly increase the odds
وما فعله ذلك هو أن زاد وعلى نحو كبير احتمالية
that newcomers would contribute to the economy.
مشاركة القادمين الجدد في الإقتصاد.
Then part two, Trudeau created the world's first policy
الجزء الثاني، خلق (ترودو) أول سياسة عالمية
of official multiculturalism to promote integration
للتعدية الثقافية الرسمية من أجل الترويج للتكامل
and the idea that diversity was the key to Canada's identity.
وفكرة أن التنوع كان هو المفتاح نحو تحقيق هوية كندا.
Now, in the years that followed, Ottawa kept pushing this message,
الآن، خلال السنوات التي تلت ذلك، حافظت ولاية (أوتاوا) على نشر هذه الرسالة،
but at the same time, ordinary Canadians
ولكن في نفس الوقت، بدأ الكنديّيون العاديّيون
soon started to see the economic, the material benefits of multiculturalism
سريعاً في رؤية الفوائد الإقتصادية والمادية للتعدية الثقافية
all around them.
في كل مكان من حولهم.
And these two influences soon combined
حيث اجتمع هذان العاملان المؤثران
to create the passionately open-minded Canada of today.
ليخلقا كندا المنفحته على نحو عاطفي التي نشهدها اليوم.
Let's now turn to another country and an even tougher problem,
دعونا الآن ننتقل إلى دولة أخرى ومشكلة أكثر صعوبة حتى،
Islamic extremism.
التطرف الإسلامي.
In 1998, the people of Indonesia took to the streets
في عام 1998، خرج الناس في إندونيسيا إلى الشوارع
and overthrew their longtime dictator, Suharto.
وأطاحوا بدكتاتورهم (سوهارتو) الحاكم منذ أمد طويل.
It was an amazing moment,
كانت لحظة مدهشة،
but it was also a scary one.
ولكنها كانت مرعبةً أيضاً.
With 250 million people,
بوجود 250 مليون نسمة،
Indonesia is the largest Muslim-majority country on Earth.
تعدّ إندونيسيا أكبر دولة ذات أغلبية مسلمة في العالم.
It's also hot, huge and unruly,
كما أنها ساخنة وضخمة وصعبة المراس أيضاً،
made up of 17,000 islands,
مكونة من 17,000 جزيرة،
where people speak close to a thousand languages.
حيث يتحدث الناس فيها قرابة الألف لغة.
Now, Suharto had been a dictator,
الآن، كان (سوهارتو) دكتاتوراً،
and a nasty one.
ودكتاتوراً بغيضاً.
But he'd also been a pretty effective tyrant,
ولكنه كان طاغيةً مؤثراً بشدة،
and he'd always been careful to keep religion out of politics.
كما أنه كان حريصاً دائماً على إبقاء الدين بعيداً عن السياسة.
So experts feared that without him keeping a lid on things,
لذلك خشي الخبراء من أنه في حال فقدان سيطرته على مجريات الأمور،
the country would explode,
فإن البلاد قد تنفجر،
or religious extremists would take over
أو قد يستولي المتطرّفون الدينيّون على السلطة
and turn Indonesia into a tropical version of Iran.
ومن ثم يحولوا إندونيسيا إلى نسخة طبق الأصل من إيران.
And that's just what seemed to happen at first.
وقد بدا ذلك وشيكاً في بادئ الأمر.
In the country's first free elections, in 1999,
في أول انتخابات حرة تشهدها البلاد في عام 1999،
Islamist parties scored 36 percent of the vote,
نالت الأحزاب الإسلامية 36% من الأصوات،
and the islands burned
واحترقت الجزر
as riots and terror attacks killed thousands.
بينما حصد الشغب والهجمات الإرهابية أرواح الآلاف.
Since then, however, Indonesia has taken a surprising turn.
ومنذ ذلك الحين، ومع ذلك، اتخذت إندونيسيا منعطفاً مفاجئاً.
While ordinary folks have grown more pious on a personal level --
في حين أصبح الناس العاديّون أكثر ورعاً على المستوى الشخصي --
I saw a lot more headscarves on a recent visit
في زيارة مؤخراً، رأيت مزيداً من الحجاب أكثر
than I would have a decade ago --
مما كنت لأراه قبل عقد من الزمان --
the country's politics have moved in the opposite direction.
سارت سياسة الدولة في الإتجاه المعاكس.
Indonesia is now a pretty decent democracy.
تعدّ إندونييسيا اليوم ديموقراطيةً جديرةً بالإحترام جداً.
And yet, its Islamist parties have steadily lost support,
ومع ذلك، فقدت أحزابها الإسلامية الدعم باستمرار،
from a high of about 38 percent in 2004
من نسبة عالية حوالي 38% في العام 2004
down to 25 percent in 2014.
هبوطاً حتى 25% في العام 2014.
As for terrorism, it's now extremely rare.
بالنسبة للتطرف، فهو شيء نادر جداً الآن.
And while a few Indonesians have recently joined ISIS,
وفي حين أن بعض الإندونسيّين انضموا مؤخراً إلى تنظيم (داعش)،
their number is tiny,
إلّا أنه رقم ضئيل،
far fewer in per capita terms
أقل بكثير من حيث نصيب الفرد
than the number of Belgians.
من رقم البلجيكيّين.
Try to think of one other Muslim-majority country
حاولوا أن تفكّروا بدولة ذات أغلبية مسلمة أخرى
that can say all those same things.
تستطيع أن تقول كل هذه الأشياء المتشابهة.
In 2014, I went to Indonesia to ask its current president,
في عام 2014، ذهبت إلى إندونيسيا لأوجّه أسئلة لرئيسها الحالي،
a soft-spoken technocrat named Joko Widodo,
تكنوقراطي معسول الكلام يدعى (جوكو ويدودو)،
"Why is Indonesia thriving when so many other Muslim states are dying?"
"ما الشيء الذي يجعل إندونيسيا تزدهر في حين أن أغلب الدول المسلمة الأخرى تحتضر؟"
"Well, what we realized," he told me,
رد علي قائلاً: "حسناً، ما لاحظناه
"is that to deal with extremism, we needed to deal with inequality first."
هو أنه من أجل معالجة التطرف، توجب علينا معالجة عدم المساواة أولاً."
See, Indonesia's religious parties, like similar parties elsewhere,
أترون، الأحزاب الدينية الإندونيسيّة مثل غيرها من الأحزاب المشابهة في أماكن أخرى،
had tended to focus on things like reducing poverty and cutting corruption.
كانت تميل إلى التركيز على أِشياء من قبيل تقليل الفقر والتخلص من الفساد.
So that's what Joko and his predecessors did too,
كان ذلك ما فعله (جوكو) وأسلافه أيضاً،
thereby stealing the Islamists' thunder.
وبالتالي سحب البساط من تحت أقدام الإسلاميّين.
They also cracked down hard on terrorism,
كما أنهم ضربوا الإرهاب بيد من حديد،
but Indonesia's democrats have learned a key lesson
ولكن الديمقراطيّين في إندونيسيا تعلموا درساً مهماً
from the dark years of dictatorship,
من سنين الدكتاتورية المظلمة،
namely that repression only creates more extremism.
وهو أن القمع لا يخلق سوى المزيد من التطرف.
So they waged their war with extraordinary delicacy.
لذلك شنّوا حروبهم بكياسة استثنائية.
They used the police instead of the army.
استعانوا بالشرطة بدلاً عن الجيش.
They only detained suspects if they had enough evidence.
كانوا يحتجزون المشتبه بهم إذا ما كانوا يمتلكون الأدلة الكافية.
They held public trials.
عقدوا محاكمات عامة.
They even sent liberal imams into the jails
حتى أنهم زجّوا بالأئمة الليبراليّين في السجون
to persuade the jihadists that terror is un-Islamic.
لإقناع المجاهدين بأن الإرهاب ليس من الإسلام في شيء.
And all of this paid off in spectacular fashion,
وجميعها آتت أكلها بطريقة مذهلة،
creating the kind of country that was unimaginable 20 years ago.
خالقةً الدولة التي ما كان من الممكن تخيلها قبل 20 عاماً.
So at this point, my optimism should, I hope,
لذلك عند هذه النقطة، يجب أن يكون تفاؤلي، أتمنى،
be starting to make a bit more sense.
عن طريق البدء في إحداث بعض التغيير.
Neither immigration nor Islamic extremism are impossible to deal with.
ليست الهجرة ولا التطرف الإسلامي أموراً يستحيل التعامل معها.
Join me now on one last trip,
شاركوني الآن في رحلة أخيرة،
this time to Mexico.
هذه المرة إلى المكسيك.
Now, of our three stories, this one probably surprised me the most,
الآن، من بين قصصنا الثلاث، ربما أدهشتني هذه إلى أبعد حد،
since as you all know,
كما تعلمون جميعاً،
the country is still struggling with so many problems.
ما تزال هذه الدول تصارع ضد عدد من المشاكل.
And yet, a few years ago, Mexico did something
ومع ذلك، قبل عدت سنين، قامت المكسيك بفعل شيء
that many other countries from France to India to the United States
دول أخرى عديدة من فرنسا حتى الهند والولايات المتحدة
can still only dream of.
ما تزال تحلم به فقط.
It shattered the political paralysis that had gripped it for years.
فقد حطمت حالة الشلل السياسي التي هيمنت عليها منذ سنين.
To understand how, we need to rewind to the year 2000,
لفهم ذلك، نحن بحاجة إلى الرجوع إلى العام 2000،
when Mexico finally became a democracy.
عندمت أصبحت المكسيك أخيراً ديموقراطية.
Rather than use their new freedoms to fight for reform,
بدلاً عن استخدام حرياتهم الجديدة لللقتال من أجل الإصلاح،
Mexico's politicians used them to fight one another.
استخدمها ساسة المكسيك لمحاربة بعضهم البعض.
Congress deadlocked, and the country's problems --
وصلت الهيئة التشريعية إلى طريق مسدود، ومشاكل البلاد --
drugs, poverty, crime, corruption --
المخدرات، والفقر، والجريمة، والفساد --
spun out of control.
خرجت عن السيطرة.
Things got so bad that in 2008,
في العالم 2008 ساءت الأمور بشدة،
the Pentagon warned that Mexico risked collapse.
حذر (البنتاغون) أن المكسيك تواجه خطر الإنهيار.
Then in 2012, this guy named Enrique Peña Nieto
بعدها في عام 2012، هذا الشاب المسمى (إنريكو بينا نييتو)
somehow got himself elected president.
وصل إلى سدة الحكم بطريقة ما.
Now, this Peña hardly inspired much confidence at first.
الآن، لم يكن (بينا) هذا يوحي بكبير ثقة في البداية.
Sure, he was handsome,
بالتأكيد، كان وسيماً،
but he came from Mexico's corrupt old ruling party, the PRI,
لكنه كان قادماً من حزب المكسيك الفاسد الحاكم منذ فترة طويلة الحزب الثوري المؤسسي
and he was a notorious womanizer.
وكان زير نساء سيئ السمعة.
In fact, he seemed like such a pretty boy lightweight
في الواقع، بدا مثل هذا الصبي الجميل خفيف الوزن
that women called him "bombón," sweetie,
وقد كانت النساء ينادينه "بومبون" العزيز،
at campaign rallies.
في مسيرات الحملة.
And yet this same bombón soon surprised everyone
ومع ذلك، بعدها بفترة أثار نفس هذا ال(بومبون) دهشت الجميع
by hammering out a truce
عندما فرض هدنة
between the country's three warring political parties.
بين أحزاب البلاد السياسية الثلاثة المتحاربة.
And over the next 18 months, they together passed
وعلى مدى الأشهر ال18 التالية، تجاوزوا معاً
an incredibly comprehensive set of reforms.
مجموعة من الإصلاحات الشاملة على نحو لا يصدق.
They busted open Mexico's smothering monopolies.
ضبطوا احتكارات المكسيك الخانقة.
They liberalized its rusting energy sector.
حرروا قطاع طاقتها الصدأ.
They restructured its failing schools, and much more.
أعادوا بناء مدارسها المتعثرة، والمزيد غيرها.
To appreciate the scale of this accomplishment,
لإدراك حجم هذه الإنجازات،
try to imagine the US Congress passing immigration reform,
حاولوا تخيل الكونغرس الأمريكي وهو يمرر إصلاحات تتعلق بالهجرة،
campaign finance reform and banking reform.
إصلاحات تتعلق بتمويل الحملات الإنتخابية وإصلاحات بنكية.
Now, try to imagine Congress doing it all at the same time.
الآن، حاولوا تخيّل الكونغرس الأمريكي يقوم بها جميعاً دفعةً واحدة.
That's what Mexico did.
كان ذلك ما فعلته المكسيك.
Not long ago, I met with Peña and asked how he managed it all.
منذ وقت ليس ببعيد، التقيت ب(بينا) وسألته كيف استطاع إدارة كل هذا.
The President flashed me his famous twinkly smile --
أبرق الرئيس في وجهي بابتسامته المشهورة المتلألئة --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and told me that the short answer was "compromiso," compromise.
وقال لي أن الإجابة القصيرة لذلك هي "compromiso" التوصل إلى تفاهم.
Of course, I pushed him for details,
بالتأكيد، طلبت منه الإستفاضة أكثر،
and the long answer that came out was essentially
وكانت الإجابة الطويلة التي صدرت منه هي في جوهرها
"compromise, compromise and more compromise."
"التسوية والتسوية والمزيد من التسوية."
See, Peña knew that he needed to build trust early,
أترون، عرف (بينا) أنه كان بحاجة إلى بناء الثقة مبكراً،
so he started talking to the opposition just days after his election.
لذلك، بدأ بالتحدث إلى المعارضة بعدها بأيام فقط من انتخابه.
To ward off pressure from special interests,
لدرء الضغوط الناتجة من المصالح الخاصة،
he kept their meetings small and secret,
أبقى على اجتماعاتهم محدودة العدد وسريّة،
and many of the participants later told me that it was this intimacy,
ولقد أخبرني العديد من المشاركين بعدها أن هذه الحميمية،
plus a lot of shared tequila,
بالإضافة إلى الكثير من شراب التكيلا،
that helped build confidence.
هي الشيء الذي ساعد على بناء الثقة.
So did the fact that all decisions had to be unanimous,
لذلك، مثّل حقيقة أن كل القرارات كان يجب أن تكون بالإجماع،
and that Peña even agreed to pass some of the other party's priorities
وقد وافق (بينا) على تمرير بعض أولويات الأحزاب الأخرى
before his own.
قبل أولوياته هو.
As Santiago Creel, an opposition senator, put it to me,
كما أخبرني عضو مجلس الشيوخ المعارض (سانتياغو كريل)،
"Look, I'm not saying that I'm special or that anyone is special,
"انظر، أنا لا أقول أنني مميز أو أن أي أحد آخر مميز،
but that group, that was special."
ولكن تلك المجموعة، كانت هي المميزة."
The proof?
الدليل؟
When Peña was sworn in, the pact held,
عندما أدّى (بينا) اليمين الدستورية، تمت التسوية
and Mexico moved forward for the first time in years.
ومضت المكسيك قدماً لأول مرة منذ سنين.
Bueno.
جيد.
So now we've seen how these three countries
رأينا الآن كيف تمكنت هذه الدول الثلاث
overcame three of their great challenges.
من تجاوز ثلاث من التحديات العظيمة التي كانت تواجهها.
And that's very nice for them, right?
وذلك شيء رائع بالنسبة لهم، أليس كذلك؟
But what good does it do the rest of us?
ولكن بماذا تفيدنا؟
Well, in the course of studying these and a bunch of other success stories,
حسناً، في سياق دراسة قصص النجاح هذه وأخرى غيرها،
like the way Rwanda pulled itself back together after civil war
مثل الطريقة التي استعادة بها رواندا عافيتها بعد حرب أهلية
or Brazil has reduced inequality,
أو البرازيل في تقليلها لعدم المساواة،
or South Korea has kept its economy growing faster and for longer
أو كوريا الجنوبية عندما حافظت على نمو اقتصادها على نحو أسرع ومستدام
than any other country on Earth,
أكثر من أي دولة أخرى على وجه الأرض،
I've noticed a few common threads.
لقد لاحظت وجود بعض المواضيع المشتركة.
Now, before describing them, I need to add a caveat.
الآن، قبل البدء في شرحها، أجد نفسي بحاجة إلى إضافة تحذير.
I realize, of course, that all countries are unique.
لاحظت، بالتأكيد، أن كل الدول فريدة من نوعها.
So you can't simply take what worked in one,
لذلك، لا يمكنك ببساطة اعتماد ما نجح مع أحدها،
port it to another and expect it to work there too.
وتصديرها إلى دولة أخرى وتوقع أن تنجح هناك أيضاً.
Nor do specific solutions work forever.
ليس هناك من حلول محددة تعمل إلى الأبد.
You've got to adapt them as circumstances change.
عليك تكييفها بينما تتغير الظروف.
That said, by stripping these stories to their essence,
لهذا، بتجريد هذه القصص إلى جوهرها،
you absolutely can distill a few common tools for problem-solving
يمكنك بمعنى الكلمة إستخلاص بعض الأدوات المشتركة لحل المشاكل
that will work in other countries
والتي ستنجح في دول أخرى
and in boardrooms
وفي مجالس الإدارة
and in all sorts of other contexts, too.
وفي كل السياقات الأخرى، أيضاً.
Number one, embrace the extreme.
رقم واحد، تقبّل التطرف.
In all the stories we've just looked at,
في كل القصص التي اتطلعنا عليها،
salvation came at a moment of existential peril.
أتى الخلاص في لحظة الخطر الوجودي.
And that was no coincidence.
ولم يكن ذلك وليد الصدفة.
Take Canada: when Trudeau took office, he faced two looming dangers.
خذ كندا كمثال: عندما تولى (ترودو) السلطة، واجه خطرين محدّقين.
First, though his vast, underpopulated country
الأول، على الرغم من اتساع بلده إلاّ أنه قليل السكان
badly needed more bodies,
وبحاجة إلى المزيد منهم،
its preferred source for white workers, Europe,
مصدرها المفضل للعمال البيض هو أوروبا،
had just stopped exporting them as it finally recovered from World War II.
والذي توقف عن تصديرهم لها بعد أن تعافى أخيراً من الحرب العالمية الثانية.
The other problem was that Canada's long cold war
كانت المشكلة الأخرى هي حربها الباردة الطويلة
between its French and its English communities
بين مجتمعاتها الفرنسية والإنجليزية
had just become a hot one.
والتي أصبحت مستعرة حينها.
Quebec was threatening to secede,
كانت كويبيك تهدد بالإنفصال،
and Canadians were actually killing other Canadians over politics.
بينما يقتل الكنديّيون بعضهم البعض بسبب السياسة.
Now, countries face crises all the time. Right?
الآن، تواجه الدول الأزمات في كل الأوقات. أليس كذلك؟
That's nothing special.
ليس شيئاً مميزاً.
But Trudeau's genius was to realize that Canada's crisis
لكن عبقرية (ترودو) كانت تكمن في إدراكه أن أزمة كندا
had swept away all the hurdles that usually block reform.
تجاوزت كل العقبات التي عادةً ما تعيق طريق الإصلاح.
Canada had to open up. It had no choice.
توجب على كندا الإنفتاح. لم يكن لديها خيار آخر.
And it had to rethink its identity.
وكان يتوجب عليها إعادة التفكير في هويتها.
Again, it had no choice.
مرة أخرى، لم يكن لديها خيار آخر.
And that gave Trudeau a once-in-a-generation opportunity
وقد أعطى ذلك (ترودو) فرصة تاريخية
to break the old rules and write new ones.
لتحطيم القواعد القديمة وكتابة أخرى جديدة.
And like all our other heroes, he was smart enough to seize it.
وككل أبطالنا السابقين، كان ذكياً بما يكفي لإنتهازها.
Number two, there's power in promiscuous thinking.
رقم إثنين، هناك قوة في التفكير المشوش
Another striking similarity among good problem-solvers
التشابه الآخر اللافت للنظر بين من يجيدون حل المشكلات
is that they're all pragmatists.
هي أنهم جميعاً عمليّيون.
They'll steal the best answers from wherever they find them,
فهم يسرقون أفضل الإجابات من أي مكان يعثرون فيه عليها،
and they don't let details
ولا يسمحون لتفاصيل
like party or ideology or sentimentality get in their way.
مثل حزب أو مذهب أو عاطفية بالوقوف في طريقهم.
As I mentioned earlier, Indonesia's democrats were clever enough
كما ذكرت من قبل، كان الديمقراطيّيون الإندونيسييون أذكياء بما يكفي
to steal many of the Islamists' best campaign promises for themselves.
لسرقة أفضل وعود حملات الإسلاميين لصالحهم.
They even invited some of the radicals into their governing coalition.
حتى أنهم دعوا لبعض المتطرفين إلى ائتلافهم الحاكم.
Now, that horrified a lot of secular Indonesians.
الآن، أثار ذلك ذعر الكثير من العلمانيين الإندونيسيّين.
But by forcing the radicals to actually help govern,
ولكن عن طريق إجبار المتطرفيين على المساعدة في الحكم،
it quickly exposed the fact that they weren't any good at the job,
سرعان ما فضح ذلك حقيقة أنهم كانوا غير جديرين بالمناصب،
and it got them mixed up in all of the grubby compromises
مما حدى بهم على الضياع وسط المساومات الوضيعة
and petty humiliations that are part of everyday politics.
والإذلالات التافهه التي هي جزء من السياسة اليومية.
And that hurt their image so badly that they've never recovered.
مما أضرّ بصورتهم على نحو سيء للغاية ولم يتعافوا بعدها.
Number three,
رقم ثلاثة،
please all of the people some of the time.
أسعد جميع الناس لبعض الوقت.
I know I just mentioned how crises can grant leaders extraordinary freedoms.
أعرف أنني ذكرت للتو كيف أن الأزمات تمنح القادة حريات استثنائية.
And that's true, but problem-solving often requires more than just boldness.
وذلك شيء حقيقي، ولكن حل المشكلات غالباً ما يتطلب أكثر من مجرد الجرأة.
It takes showing restraint, too,
فهو يتطلب إظهار ضبط النفس أيضاً،
just when that's the last thing you want to do.
عندما يكون ذلك آخر شيء تود فعله.
Take Trudeau: when he took office,
خذ (ترودو) كمثال، عندما تسلم السلطة،
he could easily have put his core constituency,
كان بوسعه بسهولة وضع دائرته الإنتخابية،
that is Canada's French community, first.
ألا وهي المجتمع الفرنسي في كندا أولاً.
He could have pleased some of the people all of the time.
كان بإمكانه إسعاد بعض الناس على الدوام.
And Peña could have used his power to keep attacking the opposition,
كما أن (بينا) كان بإمكانه استخدام قوته لمواصلة مهاجمة المعارضة،
as was traditional in Mexico.
وهو الشيء المعهود في المكسيك.
Yet he chose to embrace his enemies instead,
لكنه فضّل احتواء أعدائه بدلاً عن ذلك،
while forcing his own party to compromise.
في حين أجبر حزبه على تقديم تنازلات.
And Trudeau pushed everyone to stop thinking in tribal terms
وقد حثّ (ترودو) الجميع على عدم التفكير في الشروط القبلية
and to see multiculturalism, not language and not skin color,
بل التركيز على التعددية الثقافية، وليس اللغة ولون البشرة،
as what made them quintessentially Canadian.
مما جعلهم كنديّين على نحو مثالي.
Nobody got everything they wanted,
لم يحصل أي شخص على كل ما أراد،
but everyone got just enough that the bargains held.
ولكن كل شخص حصل على ما يكفيه لعقد الصفقات.
So at this point you may be thinking,
لذلك ربما تفكر عند هذه النقطة،
"OK, Tepperman,
"حسناً، (تيبيرمان)
if the fixes really are out there like you keep insisting,
إذا ما كانت الحلول موجودة حقاً كما ظللت تلح،
then why aren't more countries already using them?"
إذاً لماذا لا تلجأ دول أكثر إلى استخدامها؟
It's not like they require special powers to pull off.
لا يبدو أنها تتطلب قدرات خاصة لتنجح.
I mean, none of the leaders we've just looked at were superheroes.
أعني، لم يكن أي من القادة الذين اتطلعنا على قصصهم أشخاصاً خارقين،
They didn't accomplish anything on their own,
لم ينجزوا أي شيء لوحدهم،
and they all had plenty of flaws.
وكان لديهم الكثير من العيوب.
Take Indonesia's first democratic president,
خذ أول رئيس ديموقراطي لإندونيسيا،
Abdurrahman Wahid.
(عبدالرحمن وحيد).
This man was so powerfully uncharismatic
كان هذا الرجل صاحب شخصية غير جذابة على نحو كبير للغاية
that he once fell asleep
حتى أنه نام ذات مرة
in the middle of his own speech.
أثناء إلقاء خطابه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
True story.
قصة حقيقية.
So what this tells us is that the real obstacle is not ability,
إذاً ما نتعلمه من هذا أن العقبة الحقيقية ليست القدرة،
and it's not circumstances.
كما أنها ليست الظروف.
It's something much simpler.
بل شيء أبسط بكثير.
Making big changes involves taking big risks,
إحداث تغيير ملموس ينطوي على القيام بمخاطر كبيرة،
and taking big risks is scary.
والقيام بمخاطر كبيرة شيء مخيف.
Overcoming that fear requires guts,
والتغلب على ذلك الخوف يتطلب شجاعة،
and as you all know,
وكما تعلمون جميعاً،
gutsy politicians are painfully rare.
السياسيون الشجعان نادرون بشدة.
But that doesn't mean we voters
ولكن ذلك لا يعني أننا الناخبون
can't demand courage from our political leaders.
لا يمكننا مطالبة قادتنا السياسيين بالشجاعة.
I mean, that's why we put them in office in the first place.
أعني، ذلك هو سبب وضعنا لهم في سدة الحكم من الأساس.
And given the state of the world today, there's really no other option.
وبالنظر إلى وضع العالم اليوم، ليس هناك من حل آخر حقاً.
The answers are out there,
الإجابات موجودة هناك،
but now it's up to us
ولكن الآن الأمر متروك لنا
to elect more women and men
لانتخاب المزيد من الرجال والنساء
brave enough to find them,
يتمتعون بالشجاعة الكافية للعثور عليها،
to steal them
ولسرقتها
and to make them work.
ولجعلها تعمل.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)